Now, let's look into the common pricing frameworks
لننظر الآن في أطر التسعير الشائع
that are used in the freelancing world.
استخدامها في عالم العمل الحر.
Now, by pricing framework here,
ما نعنيه بإطار التسعير هنا هو
what we mean is the structure within which you as a freelancer would get paid.
الهيكل الذي بداخله سوف يتم دفع الأموال لك.
The two types that we discussed now would make this clearer.
وسوف يوضح المثالان اللذان سنناقشهما الآن هذا الأمر أكثر.
One kind of pricing framework is called fixed cost.
أحد أنواع أطر التسعير يدعى التكلفة الثابتة.
As the name suggests,
وهو كما يوحي اسمه
this means that the total cost of the project
يعني أن التكلفة الكلية للمشروع
end-to-end is fixed at the start of the project.
من أوله لآخره تتحدد في بداية المشروع.
For example, you could say that you charge $100 to add a module to an existing website,
على سبيل المثال، من الممكن أن تطالب العميل بـ 100 دولار لإضافة نموذج لموقع إلكتروني قائم،
or you would charge $400 to build a static website,
أو 400 دولار لبناء موقع ثابت،
or maybe $3,000 to build a web application.
أو ربما 3,000 دولار لإنشاء تطبيق ويب.
All these are fixed costs for the project
كل هذه تكاليف ثابتة للمشروع
that you have decided to work on for the client.
الذي قررت العمل لدى العميل عليه.
Then the client will pay you after the work is completed.
وسوف يدفع لك العميل بعد انتهائك من المشروع.
All these are fixed costs for the project
كل هذه تكاليف ثابتة للمشروع
that the client will pay you after the work is done.
سوف يدفعها العميل بعد الانتهاء من العمل.
On the other hand,
على الجانب الآخر
time and material is the other pricing framework
فالوقت والمادة هما الإطار التسعيري الآخر
which requires a fixed rate for the work that you do.
والذي يتطلب سعر ثابت للعمل الذي تقوم به.
This rate is usually set as an hourly rate.
وهذا السعر يتحدد عادةً كأجر في الساعة.
For example, you could set your rate to $25 an hour,
يمكنك على سبيل المثال أن تحدد سعرك بـ 25 دولار في الساعة
which means you'll get $25 for every hour that you spend working on the client's task,
وهو ما يعني أنك سوف تتقاضى أجرًا قيمته 25 دولار لكل ساعة تقضيها في العمل على مشروع العميل،
or $40 an hour,
أو تحدده بـ 40 دولار في الساعة
or maybe $110 an hour.
أو ربما بـ 110 دولار في الساعة.
Fixed-cost project is primarily work-based,
مشاريع التكلفة الثابتة تكون عادةً مبنية على العمل،
you get paid for the work that you have done whose cost is pre-decided.
فأنت تتقاضى أجرك عن العمل الذي أنجزته والذي تتحدد تكلفته مسبقًا.
On the other hand, as we saw,
ولكن على الصعيد الآخر كما رأينا
time and material is time-based,
فإطار الوقت والمادة مبني على الوقت،
you are paid based on the time you spend on the task.
فأنت تتقاضى أجرك بناء على الوقت الذي قضيته على العمل.
Keep in mind though,
ولكن تذكر
that some projects may put a cap on the maximum number of hours that you can spend there.
أن بعض المشاريع تضع سقفًا لأقصى عدد من الساعات التي يمكنك أن تقضيها على العمل.
But what gets done in those hours cannot be fixed since this is
ولكن ما يتم عمله لا يمكن إصلاحه حيث أن هذا النموذج
a time-based model where you are paid for the time you spend on the project.
قائم على الوقت حيث تتقاضى أجرك عن الوقت الذي تقضيه على المشروع.
If you're thinking about what's the material bid in time and material,
إذا كنت تفكر في ماهية الجزء الذي يتكلم عن المادة في إطار الوقت والمادة
that's the next point of difference.
فهذه هي نقطة الاختلاف التالية.
In fixed cost, the cost is inclusive of any overheads that are required for the project.
في إطار التكلفة الثابتة تشمل التكلفة أي نفقات إضافية يتطلبها المشروع.
You would not build them separately since the total cost of the project
فأنت لن تنشئهم بشكل منفصل حيث أن التكلفة الكلية للمشروع
is already fixed and the client has already budgeted for it.
مثبتة بالفعل ووضعها العميل بالفعل في ميزانيته.
Whereas in time and material,
ولكن في إطار الوقت والمادة
you will build any overheads on actuals to the client since it is not
فسوف تبني أي تكاليف غير المباشرة للعميل على القيم الفعلية حيث أن
a fixed cost project and you're billing for any time
تكلفة المشروع ليست ثابتة وأنت تحاسب على أي وقت
or material that you use for the project as you go along.
أو مادة تستخدمهما للمشروع وأنت تمضي قدمًا فيه.
Now, what do we really mean by overheads, you might ask.
من الممكن أن تتسائل عما نعنيه حقًا بالنفقات الإضافية.
Overheads are things like any special hardware that you use for the project,
التكاليف غير المباشرة هي أي معدات تستخدمها للمشروع
like a webcam when you're developing an image sensing application,
مثل كاميرا الويب حينما يكون ما تنشئه هو تطبيق استشعار للصورة،
or any specific software license that you need to obtain for the client's project,
أو أي تراخيص لبرمجيات محددة تحتاج للحصول عليها من أجل مشروع العميل
like Microsoft Word license to create and edit
مثل رخصة Microsoft Word للإنشاء والتعديل
documents or a paid WordPress stream for a website.
الوثائق أو WordPress Stream مدفوع لموقع إلكتروني.
We discussed the two kinds of pricing structures that are
لقد ناقشنا نوعان من هياكل التسعير التي
generally used by freelancers to build their clients.
تستخدم عمومًا بين موظفي العم الحر لبناء قاعدة عملائهم.
I would say spend some time to look at these two types of
أقترح أن تقضي بعض الوقت في النظر في هذين النوعين
pricing structures in this chart and try to internalize them.
من الهياكل التسعيرية الموضحان في هذا الرسم التخطيطي وأن تستوعبهما.
You'll see these coming handy whenever you work with new clients.
سوف ترى أنهما سوف ينفعانك كلما عملت مع عملاء جدد.